<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Cal Murgu</title>
        <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Cal Murgu</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://calmurgu.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Confessions of a reformed Omeka acolyte. Minimalist options for digital exhibitions</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/11/confessions-of-a-reformed-omeka-acolyte.-minimalist-options-for-digital-exhibitions/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/11/confessions-of-a-reformed-omeka-acolyte.-minimalist-options-for-digital-exhibitions/</guid>
            <description>While a Digital Projects Coordinator at the University of Windsor in 2015-16, I remember thinking that Omeka would revolutionize the way we create and teach about digital exhibits, metadata, and the subtle acts involved in digital collecting. Here was a relatively lightweight CMS that enabled us to spin up new instances almost immediately. With set-up a breeze, we could focus our attention on the intellectual work of arrangement, description, and narrative.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While a Digital Projects Coordinator at the University of Windsor in 2015-16, I remember thinking that Omeka would revolutionize the way we create and teach about digital exhibits, metadata, and the subtle acts involved in digital collecting. Here was a relatively lightweight CMS that enabled us to spin up new instances almost immediately. With set-up a breeze, we could focus our attention on the intellectual work of arrangement, description, and narrative. I was also excited by the opportunity that Omeka offered for pedagogy. At the same time as the public humanities picked up steam, Omeka lowered the barrier of entry for humanities instructors to introduce digital scholarship and create assignments revolving around the platform. In this context, and perhaps as a result of the interesting and deep relationship that I had created with the faculty at Windsor, we found ourselves in the classroom more often.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Oh yeah, we'll just spin up an Omeka instance and be on our way. Digital exhibits? Sure. Collectons? Sure. Custom themes? Sure.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I became an Omeka acolyte.</p>
<p>I'm writing this because I recognize a similar optimism about recent software that embrace and advance the &lsquo;minimalist computing&rsquo; paradigm. Here I'm thinking specifically of Wax and CollectionBuilder.</p>
<p>Wax is essentially a Jekyll theme that uses Ruby gems to create &ldquo;an extensible workflow for producing scholarly exhibitions with minimal computing principles.&rdquo; The exhibition sites created by Wax are static, meaning that they consist of flat HTML, CSS, and JavaScript files that do not require a database for file storage. As Wax documentation makes clear, this apprach &ldquo;makes them cheaper, safer, and generally easier to maintain—as long as you’re willing to learn some new skills.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Arguably the skills needed to create Wax sites are more basic than those needed to run an Omeka instance. Wax involves learning a little about modern web development, the command line, spreadsheets, data management, GitHub (if you choose to use Github for hosting), and some plain text editing.</p>
<p>For more on Wax, visit their <a href="https://minicomp.github.io/wiki/wax/">documentation</a>.
<img src="https://minicomp.github.io/wiki/assets/wax_workflow.jpeg" alt="Wax Workflow"></p>
<p>CollectionBuilder is an even more robust exhibit builder that offers additional functionality &ldquo;out of the box.&rdquo; CollectionBuilder also leverages the power of Jekyll and Ruby gems, as well as some additional open source Javascript libraries — like Leaflet — to create static websites of interactive digital exhibits rich in metadata. Similar to Wax, CollectionBuilder requires some knowledge of the command line, basic web development principles, and metadata. Check out their webpage for documentation and <a href="https://collectionbuilder.github.io/">examples</a>.</p>
<p>These are two examples of approaches inspired by the &lsquo;minimalist computing&rsquo; paradigm put forward by <a href="http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/">Alex Gil</a> and <a href="https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2016/10/03/tldr/">Jentery Sayers</a>. The paradigm is centered on a set of questions that we must ask ourselves and our collaborators before jumping headfirst into an exciting new project. They are:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“What do we need?”; “What don’t we need?”; “What do we want?”; “What don’t we want?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The answer to this question can now be modified by the adjectives &ldquo;minimal&rdquo; or &ldquo;maximal&rdquo;: &ldquo;minimal design&rdquo; / &ldquo;minimal dependencies&rdquo; / &ldquo;maximal collaboration&rdquo; / &ldquo;maximal accessibility.&rdquo; We've reached a point in the ebb and flow of design and aesthetics where minimalism is appreciated and encouraged. Moreover, with tools like Wax and CollectionBuilder, we have the ability to create elaborate projects that feature attractive and accessible front-ends without the added infrastructural baggage. As Gil writes, the culture of &ldquo;user friendly&rdquo; interfaces has</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip;also led to some basic misunderstandings of what computers can and should do. In the case of writing, the expectation that you should get what you see continues to distance producers from their tools.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think we can extend this to critique the way we &ldquo;build&rdquo; content management systems that privilege easy administration (GUIs, DBs) over direct interaction with the process of building (a command line, a spreadsheet, a text editor). Ultimately, I think this is an exciting period for library services as well as an opportunity to refocus our library instruction. We've been experimenting with integrating minimalist solutions in our workflow. You can see some of our work with Wax <a href="https://dss.ncf.edu/pei/">here</a> and <a href="https://dss.ncf.edu/constitution/">here</a>.</p>
<p>I'm currently in the process of integrating Wax and CollectionBuilder in my instructional collaborations with willing faculty. Some students have expressed interest in creating digital exhibits, as well. For example, a student this term wanted to create an interactive digital exhibit of 49 printing shirt screens made and used by New College of Florida students and staff. As they state on the project's main page, &ldquo;Screenprinting is a printing method used to reproduce designs on fabric, primarily t-shirts. The designs on the screenprints below would have been reproduced multiple times for different people. New College students made these printing screens because they thought the design was important enough to not only produce but reproduce and distribute. Therefore, by looking at these screens we can find out what kind of things New College students thought important enough to commemorate.&rdquo; You can check that out <a href="https://carolinenewberg.github.io/ncf-screenprints/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Building on this, in the Spring I'll work with a class on creating a collaborative digital collection using CollectionBuilder for an <em>Introduction to the Humanities</em> class. The idea is to follow through the entire collection lifecycle, from the archive, through digitization and description, to the technical components (including metadata, spreadsheets, and some command line) of digital exhibit building.</p>
<p>Finally, I've noticed a gradual change in how I approach digital scholarship. In my current role I oversee the technical as well as the pedagogical side of digital projects. Sustainability, minimialism, and small technical-footprints are important principles that orient my work as I seek to shepherd projects that will add value (to a person, a class, a community, etc) at a reasonable cost with respect to technical and human resourcing. I also accept that these projects will not last forever, but they might outlast me in this position. I think I'm responsible for ensuring that the next person in this role inherits a clean (leave my desk out of this!) and sustainable environment that allows them to continue/pivot/change without interruption.</p>
<p>The work that I did with Omeka was key because it shaped the way I approached library involvement in the classroom. Many of the sites we worked on then are still online, though they've started to show their age. And so, while many things have changed since, the energy that I receive from instruction sessions that go beyond library databases has remained a constant. Software like Wax and CollectionBuilder will only work to augment the connection between library technology and the classroom, and that, to me, is an exciting proposition.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Visualizing Librarian/Faculty Interaction Data with R</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/07/visualizing-librarian/faculty-interaction-data-with-r/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/07/visualizing-librarian/faculty-interaction-data-with-r/</guid>
            <description>Thanks to Jesse Sadler and their blog for this information. It was very, very helpful for a novice like me. I find that I learn best when I have a specific project to practice with, with tangible goals that I can associate with my work. This is an example of one such project.
This post is an attempt at using R to develop a process for using Librarian/Faculty interaction data in a meaningful way.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to Jesse Sadler and their
<a href="https://www.jessesadler.com/post/network-analysis-with-r/">blog</a> for
this information. It was very, very helpful for a novice like me. I
find that I learn best when I have a specific project to practice with,
with tangible goals that I can associate with my work. This is an
example of one such project.</p>
<p>This post is an attempt at using R to develop a process for using
Librarian/Faculty interaction data in a meaningful way. This is part of
a larger project that I’m working on that seeks to build on the
intersection between Libraries, data, and customer relationship
management principles. If we think of library interactions from a
perspective informed by CRM, we can more easily think of librarian’s
work as part of larger networks of scholarship, communication, and
learning. It also implicitly argues that librarians need to think more
about nurturing relationships with faculty, as well as building new ones
with faculty that have been ignored, and rekindling new ones with
faculty who held relationships with librarians that are no longer
around. Network theory lends itself nicely to this approach. So, let’s
dive in.</p>
<h2 id="plan">Plan</h2>
<p>Today we’ll visualize a sample set of library interaction data using the
visNetwork package. At my library, we use LibInsight Lite to track
various interaction types, including instruction, research help, digital
scholarship support, and so on. The data that we’ll use here has been
randomly generated.</p>
<p>First, we need to define <em>nodes</em> and <em>edges</em>. Nodes are our nouns
(people). Edges are our verbs (interactions).</p>
<p>We’ll begin by first loading one of two important packages, and then
we’ll load our interaction data, like so:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r"><span style="color:#a6e22e">library</span>(tidyverse)
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## ── Attaching packages ───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse 1.2.1 ──

## ✔ ggplot2 3.1.0       ✔ purrr   0.3.2  
## ✔ tibble  2.1.1       ✔ dplyr   0.8.0.1
## ✔ tidyr   0.8.3       ✔ stringr 1.4.0  
## ✔ readr   1.3.1       ✔ forcats 0.4.0

## ── Conflicts ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse_conflicts() ──
## ✖ dplyr::filter() masks stats::filter()
## ✖ dplyr::lag()    masks stats::lag()
</code></pre>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">data <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">read_csv</span>(<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">refined-data.csv&#34;</span>)
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## Parsed with column specification:
## cols(
##   id = col_double(),
##   Date = col_character(),
##   `IP Address` = col_character(),
##   `Internal Notes` = col_logical(),
##   Instructors = col_character(),
##   `Course Number` = col_character(),
##   Title = col_character(),
##   Faculty = col_character()
## )
</code></pre>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">data
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## # A tibble: 199 x 8
##       id Date  `IP Address` `Internal Notes` Instructors `Course Number`
##    &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;chr&gt; &lt;chr&gt;        &lt;lgl&gt;            &lt;chr&gt;       &lt;chr&gt;          
##  1   160 8/22… 131.247.152… NA               GenevieYur… POLS 3260      
##  2   853 6/13… 131.247.152… NA               AngelTavar… Drop In        
##  3   453 2/1/… 131.247.152… NA               LibbieAlda… Drop In        
##  4    98 11/2… 131.247.152… NA               RainaReid   &lt;NA&gt;           
##  5    72 8/9/… 131.247.153… NA               LawandaPlu… Telephone      
##  6   105 1/2/… 131.247.152… NA               RegenaEhrl… &lt;NA&gt;           
##  7   184 3/14… 131.247.152… NA               AlisaGreat… &lt;NA&gt;           
##  8   219 2/8/… 131.247.152… NA               YevetteCoc… WRTG 3380      
##  9   220 2/8/… 131.247.152… NA               GenevieYur… WRTG 2100      
## 10   126 1/31… 131.247.152… NA               AngelTavar… WRTG 2100      
## # … with 189 more rows, and 2 more variables: Title &lt;chr&gt;, Faculty &lt;chr&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>We’ve successfuly loaded our data into our dataframe. Let’s check to see
the object and class types.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r"><span style="color:#a6e22e">typeof</span>(data)
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## [1] &quot;list&quot;
</code></pre>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r"><span style="color:#a6e22e">class</span>(data)
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## [1] &quot;spec_tbl_df&quot; &quot;tbl_df&quot;      &quot;tbl&quot;         &quot;data.frame&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>Next we’ll create the node list from the data table. The <em>node list</em> is
a list of unique IDs representing a particular noun. So, for example,
each name - say, Cal Murgu - has a unique ID used to identify it
numerically - 01. We’ll create a list of nodes for names in
“Instructors” and “Faculty.” Another example could me “To” and “From” in
a network of letters. Basically you want to think about the two nodes or
vertices that are interacting with each other through links or edges
(that’s next).</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">instructors <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> data <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">distinct</span>(Instructors) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">rename</span>(label <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> Instructors)
  
instructors <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">mutate</span>(instructors, groups <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Librarians&#34;</span>)

instructors
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## # A tibble: 9 x 1
##   label          
##   &lt;chr&gt;          
## 1 GenevieYurick  
## 2 AngelTavares   
## 3 LibbieAldana   
## 4 RainaReid      
## 5 LawandaPlunkett
## 6 RegenaEhrlich  
## 7 AlisaGreathouse
## 8 YevetteCockrill
## 9 JamesKulick
</code></pre>
<p>We pipe (%&gt;%, which basically means using the output of one function as
an input for another) the data table that we just loaded, specify the
“Instructors” column, and create a new table with those values with
“label” as a column header. We also add a column called &ldquo;groups&rdquo; and populate it with the value &ldquo;Librarians&rdquo;. And again for Faculty.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">faculty <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> data <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">distinct</span>(Faculty) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">rename</span>(label <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> Faculty)
  
faculty <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">mutate</span>(faculty, groups <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Faculty&#34;</span>)
</code></pre></div><p>Now that we have two dataframes, one for instructors and one for
faculty, we need to join them using the join command.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">nodes <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">full_join</span>(instructors, faculty)
nodes
</code></pre></div><p>Now we have one table with one column which includes the names of every
individual in this network. However, we need to add a column with unique
IDs to this dataframe. To do so we’ll use the <em>rowid_to_column</em>
function.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">nodes <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> nodes <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">rowid_to_column</span>(<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">id&#34;</span>)

nodes
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## # A tibble: 154 x 2
##       id label          
##    &lt;int&gt; &lt;chr&gt;          
##  1     1 GenevieYurick  
##  2     2 AngelTavares   
##  3     3 LibbieAldana   
##  4     4 RainaReid      
##  5     5 LawandaPlunkett
##  6     6 RegenaEhrlich  
##  7     7 AlisaGreathouse
##  8     8 YevetteCockrill
##  9     9 JamesKulick    
## 10    10 AleciaGatlin   
## # … with 144 more rows
</code></pre>
<p>Great!</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">nodes <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">mutate</span>(nodes, title <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> label)

nodes
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## # A tibble: 200 x 4
##       id label           group title          
##    &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;chr&gt;           &lt;chr&gt; &lt;chr&gt;          
##  1    95 AleciaGatlin    F-HUM AleciaGatlin   
##  2   159 AnnabelleLord   F-HUM AnnabelleLord  
##  3   118 AshlieRepp      F-HUM AshlieRepp     
##  4   200 BernitaHambrick F-HUM BernitaHambrick
##  5   152 BonnieHunsicker F-HUM BonnieHunsicker
##  6    23 BrookeCloninger F-HUM BrookeCloninger
##  7    92 CaitlinMagers   F-HUM CaitlinMagers  
##  8    89 CandiLamothe    F-HUM CandiLamothe   
##  9    85 CarltonMaass    F-HUM CarltonMaass   
## 10    93 ChanaLefebvre   F-HUM ChanaLefebvre  
## # … with 190 more rows
</code></pre>
<p>Notice that I added an additional column using the <em>mutate</em>
function, with column name “title” and with values that are equal to the
value of the “label” column. You’ll see why that’s important later.</p>
<p>Now, let’s create the edges table (or links). A very similar process.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">
per_act <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> data <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">group_by</span>(Instructors, Faculty) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">summarise</span>(weight <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">n</span>()) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">ungroup</span>()

per_act

</code></pre></div><pre><code>## # A tibble: 170 x 3
##    Instructors     Faculty           weight
##    &lt;chr&gt;           &lt;chr&gt;              &lt;int&gt;
##  1 AlisaGreathouse AlvinBodden            1
##  2 AlisaGreathouse AmyTicknor             1
##  3 AlisaGreathouse BerenicePeaslee        1
##  4 AlisaGreathouse BrynnAdrian            1
##  5 AlisaGreathouse CaitlinMagers          1
##  6 AlisaGreathouse CharoletteEldreth      1
##  7 AlisaGreathouse ChristianDant          1
##  8 AlisaGreathouse CorettaEhrmann         1
##  9 AlisaGreathouse CorinneCurd            2
## 10 AlisaGreathouse CraigPonte             2
## # … with 160 more rows
</code></pre>
<p>First we pipe the <em>data</em> table and group two columns, Instructors and
Faculty, using the <em>group_by</em> function. Group_by doesn’t give us any
quantitative value about what was grouped. The <em>summarise</em> function
gives us the weight of the relationship between Instructors and Faculty.
In other words, the summarise function tells us, in this case, how many
times an instructor did <em>something</em> with a faculty member.</p>
<p>Here’s another example that helped me understand these two functions, if
you’re still wondering what the hecko.</p>
<p>Let’s say you have a dataframe (df) which has US states (states) and
cities (cities) and population (population) in each city in three
columns.</p>
<p>Running:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">df <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span> 
 <span style="color:#a6e22e">group_by</span>(state) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span> 
 <span style="color:#a6e22e">summarise </span>(pop <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">sum</span>(population) <span style="color:#f92672">%\&gt;%</span>
 <span style="color:#a6e22e">ungroup</span>()
</code></pre></div><p>will give you the population rolled up by
state. For more, check this <a href="https://www.quora.com/What-does-the-group_by-function-in-R-do">link</a>.</p>
<p>The problem is that instead of numerical IDs, we have labels denoting
who is an instructor and who is a faculty member. Let’s change labels to
IDs using a <em>join</em>.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">edges <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> per_act <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span> 
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">left_join</span>(nodes, by <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">c</span>(<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Instructors&#34;</span> <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">label&#34;</span>)) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span> 
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">rename</span>(from <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> id)

edges <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> edges <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span> 
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">left_join</span>(nodes, by <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">c</span>(<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Faculty&#34;</span> <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">label&#34;</span>)) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span> 
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">rename</span>(to <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> id)
</code></pre></div><p>What we’re asking here is for R to link (join) the “Instructors” and
“Faculty” label with the label’s unique ID in nodes.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">edges <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">select</span>(edges, from, to, weight)
</code></pre></div><p>For a reason that will become evident in a second, we need to <em>mutate</em>
the edges table and add an additional column to describe the type of
activity. For the sake of convenience, I’ve listed all values under
“title” as “instruction,” but in reality these can include research
consultations, committees, venting, etc.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">edges <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">mutate</span>(edges, title <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Instruction&#34;</span>)

edges
</code></pre></div><pre><code>## # A tibble: 170 x 4
##     from    to weight title      
##    &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;dbl&gt;  &lt;int&gt; &lt;chr&gt;      
##  1     7    45      1 Instruction
##  2     7   103      1 Instruction
##  3     7   187      1 Instruction
##  4     7   145      1 Instruction
##  5     7    92      1 Instruction
##  6     7    79      1 Instruction
##  7     7    54      1 Instruction
##  8     7   123      1 Instruction
##  9     7    72      2 Instruction
## 10     7   136      2 Instruction
## # … with 160 more rows
</code></pre>
<p>That’s it! So we have a dataframe with three integer columns and one
char column. We can now graph this network!</p>
<h2 id="visnetwork">visNetwork</h2>
<p>A simple command for a simple graph.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r"><span style="color:#a6e22e">library</span>(visNetwork)

<span style="color:#a6e22e">visNetwork</span>(nodes, edges)
</code></pre></div><!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<iframe src="https://calmurgu.com/lessons/net1.html" width="100%" height="637"></iframe>

<p>This is a great interactive visualization. Notice a few things. When you
hover over a node, a tooltip will show up rendering the value of the
“title” label that we added earlier in the nodes table. More
importantly, colors denote different groups (librarians in blue, etc).</p>
<p>What else can we do? Let’s add bunch of different stuff to make this viz
a little cooler.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r">network <span style="color:#f92672">&lt;-</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">visNetwork</span>(nodes, edges, width<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">600px&#34;</span>, main <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Sample Network&#34;</span>, submain <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">2016 - 2019 Instruction Interactions&#34;</span>, footer <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Fig. 1, minimal example&#34;</span>) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">visLegend</span>() <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">visGroups</span>(groupname <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">Librarian&#34;</span>, color <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">darkblue&#34;</span>, shape <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">square&#34;</span>) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">visGroups</span>(groupname <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">F-HUM&#34;</span>, color <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">red&#34;</span>, shape <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">triangle&#34;</span>) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">visOptions</span>(highlightNearest <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#66d9ef">TRUE</span>, selectedBy <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">group&#34;</span>, nodesIdSelection <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#66d9ef">TRUE</span>) <span style="color:#f92672">%&gt;%</span>
  <span style="color:#a6e22e">visEdges</span>(arrows <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">middle&#34;</span>)

network
</code></pre></div><iframe src="https://calmurgu.com/lessons/net2.html" width="100%" height="637"></iframe>

<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>That’s one nice network. Let’s save and export as an .html page to
share.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-r" data-lang="r"><span style="color:#a6e22e">visSave</span>(network, file <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;</span><span style="color:#e6db74">network.html&#34;</span>)
</code></pre></div><p>That’s it!</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>It&#39;s time to go, Jeff</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/02/its-time-to-go-jeff/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/02/its-time-to-go-jeff/</guid>
            <description>When Jeffrey Beall retired from the Auroria Library at the University of Colorado at Denver in March 2018, half of the scholarly publishing world applauded him for his efforts against &amp;ldquo;predatory publishers.&amp;rdquo; The other half let out a massive sigh of relief. Beall&#39;s retirement succeeded a prolonged period of scandal in some academic circles.
In the years leading up to his retirement, Beall began to receive increasingly negative attention for his now infamous &amp;ldquo;Beall&#39;s list,&amp;rdquo; a blacklist of potentially predatory publishers that he himself had curated since 2008 (presumably on his free time, and not while working at the Auroria Library).</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When Jeffrey Beall retired from the Auroria Library at the University of Colorado at Denver in March 2018, half of the scholarly publishing world applauded him for his efforts against &ldquo;predatory publishers.&rdquo; The other half let out a massive sigh of relief. Beall's retirement succeeded a prolonged period of scandal in some academic circles.</p>
<p>In the years leading up to his retirement, Beall began to receive increasingly negative attention for his now infamous &ldquo;Beall's list,&rdquo; a blacklist of potentially predatory publishers that he himself had curated since 2008 (<em>presumably</em> on his free time, and not while working at the Auroria Library). The list, criticized by <a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2013/10/04/open-access-sting-reveals-deception-missed-opportunities/">some</a> for &ldquo;falsely accusing nearly one in five as being a &lsquo;potential, possible, or probable predatory scholarly open access publisher&rsquo; on appearances alone,&rdquo; attracted the enimty of scholars and publishers. And this at a time when the open access movement was picking up momentum. Following a series of altercations with several publishers, and after serious threats of civil litigation, Beall took down his website in 2017 and licked his wounds.</p>
<p>Beall had been relatively quiet since threats of civil damages threatened him and his institution, save for a handful of papers related to predatory publishing in niche publications. That is until February 7th, 2019, when Beall took aim at something altogether different: academic librarianship, the profession that he had benefited from for so long, and the one that ultimately left him in the cold.</p>
<p>In his recent <em>THE</em> op-ed (<a href="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/opinion/glamorised-study-halls-do-not-need-army-librarians">&ldquo;Glamorised study halls do not need an army of librarians,&quot;</a>) Beall makes a case against academic librarians. The premise is painfuly simple and underdeveloped: academic librarians are a clear symptom of a bloated academy and an unnecessary element of the modern university. According to Beall, the rise of the internet should have decreased the number of academic librarians since the emancipatory potential of the web has enabled &ldquo;free databases such as Google Scholar&rdquo; yet</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Government data show that the number of librarians overall in the US has remained about the same since 2003, and the profession is even expected to expand over the next decade.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For Beall and his alleged sample of students and faculty, the only &ldquo;librarians who matter are those who pay the invoices for the proprietary online research databases, and those who ensure that they are not offline.&rdquo; The very nature of the academic library, as a space of academic rigor, is in question, too. With &ldquo;lounge-like interiors&rdquo; and trendy cafes which apparently are nothing more than &ldquo;elite social clubs, offering opportunities for drinking coffee — an endless supply of cappuccino on tap — and finding dates,&rdquo; libraries, like the folks who walk and talk in its sacred corridors, have embraced anti-intellectualism.</p>
<p>The second half of his op-ed could be misinterpreted as a rough draft of Jordan Peterson's writing (and they're both rather fond of creating, <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/quicktakes/2017/11/13/professor-abandons-plan-list-%E2%80%98neo-marxist-course-content%E2%80%99">and subsequently abandoning</a>, blacklists). As Beall writes,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>university librarians are left-wing zealots and often bemoan the cost of proprietary library databases and journal subscriptions&hellip; Meanwhile, their diminishing workloads have freed them to spend large parts of their days on Twitter, advocating for social justice causes, signalling virtue by retweeting hate speech directed at Donald Trump.
This prominence and homogeneity of leftist ideology is reflected at library conferences. Increasingly, events such as those put on by the American Library Association are more like meetings of the Democratic Party platform committees.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This diatribe is followed by an abrupt turn to fiduciary management. &ldquo;With student debt in excess of $1 trillion,&rdquo; he writes, &ldquo;it is surely immoral for universities and colleges to be spending so highly&rdquo; on resources that can be easily replaced by the internet. We can all agree with Beall when he writes that &ldquo;The cost of university education in the US must urgently be brought down.&rdquo; His solution? To turn his back on the profession that turned its back on him: &ldquo;Pruning a bloated and hypocritical profession that has seriously lost its way would be an excellent place to start.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I'm not sure what upsets me more: that Beall thinks that Google Scholar is a &ldquo;free database&rdquo; (it's not, reader), or that he doesn't know that a cappuccino is a type of brew that does not come from a tap.</p>
<p>The worry with op-eds such as these is that those who pen them might be on to something, tapping into and amplyfing a cultural zeitgeist. I do not think that's happening here, reader. Beall's op-ed reads less like what a seasoned librarian trained in research and scholarship would write, and more like the napkin scrawls of someone who's had one too many vodka sodas. His claims are outdated, unfounded, and undocumented. Beall longs for the ascetic academic library of old — where library work was purposefully obscured from faculty and students — despite not having the privilege of working in one anylonger. He assumes that information is accessible, yet ignores the practical, technical, and financial implications of the digital. He disregards new and emerging services, like digital scholarship, critical information literacy instruction, and data services, to name a few, as well as the metadata work that is arguably more critical now than ever before. He sees progressive politics and empathy as negative characteristics, choosing instead to promote austerity and conservitism. Now that Beall is no longer in the candyshop, he'd like to have it demolished.</p>
<p>In 2014, Wayne Bivens-Tatum, librarian at Princeton University, <a href="https://www.triple-c.at/index.php/tripleC/article/view/617/574">published a rebutall to Beall's critique of open access in <em>tripleC</em>. </a> Taken out of its context, Biven-Tatum's conclusion is just as apt, if not more so:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[Beall's] argument fails because the sweeping generalizations with no supporting evidence render it unsound. Formally, the argument fails because its improperly distributed terms when in syllogistic form render it invalid. Thus, the overall argument is neither sound nor valid, which for an argument is about as bad as it gets.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On library jobs</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2018/07/on-library-jobs/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2018/07/on-library-jobs/</guid>
            <description>This post is primarily for graduate students in LIS that are looking for some anecdotal information about what it’s like to look for work in the information field. It&#39;s a pretty nasty proposition. In general, this post is like many others in an emerging genre, prompted by Melanie Stefan&#39;s &amp;ldquo;A CV of Failures&amp;rdquo; and Johanes Haushofer&#39;s &amp;ldquo;CV of Failures,&amp;quot; which attempt to shine a spotlight on all of the things academics apply for and fail to get, be it a grant, scholarship, publication, or job.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is primarily for graduate students in LIS that are looking for some anecdotal information about what it’s like to look for work in the information field. It's a pretty nasty proposition. In general, this post is like many others in an emerging genre, prompted by Melanie Stefan's <a href="https://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/articles/10.1038/nj7322-467a">&ldquo;A CV of Failures&rdquo;</a> and Johanes Haushofer's <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/education/2016/apr/30/cv-of-failures-princeton-professor-publishes-resume-of-his-career-lows">&ldquo;CV of Failures,&quot;</a> which attempt to shine a spotlight on all of the things academics apply for and fail to get, be it a grant, scholarship, publication, or job. As Johanes Haushofer writes,</p>
<blockquote>
<p>most of what I try fails, but these failures are often invisible, while the successes are visible. I have noticed that this sometimes gives others the impression that most things work out for me. As a result, they are
more likely to attribute their own failures to themselves, rather than the fact that the world is stochastic,
applications are crapshoots, and selection committees and referees have bad days.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I kept a detailed record of applications throughout my job hunt (including institution, salary, career-level, location). You’ll find a summary of that data illustrated below in a few different ways. If you're interested in the specifics, including copies of cover letters, get in touch (although you'd only be getting a copy of something that was ultimately unsuccessful).</p>
<p>When I first started to look for work in academic libraries in November 2017 I was hopeful about the entire process. I was selective about the positions to which I applied, choosing only those that really resonated with me — geography was no barrier. Starting in January 2018 the rate at which I submitted applications increased. At the same time, my criteria for an ideal job which at one time was pretty specific  gradually became less so. As months passed and successive interviews resulted in absolutely nothing I started to question that initial confidence. I also accepted that the value system within the academy doesn’t necessarily translate outside of it. It did not really help that well-meaning and kind individuals would say things like, “You’ll find something in no time!” or, my personal favourite, “Someone will snap you up soon!” Perhaps if potential candidates were all entered into a large pool, and hiring committees scrutinized all of their CVs in some systematic and equitable way, then the concept of “snapping you up” would apply.</p>
<p>Job hunting while still in school is an altogether different predicament than job hunting while unemployed: the stress of joblessness is negated by your student “status.” For example, as a student, you can rationalize that first pint at the graduate pub as a post-class treat and the second as an intellectual exercise (how else can you tolerate the term ‘Kafkaesque’?) When you’re no longer a student there’s very little to shield you from the physiological and financial stressors of joblessness (apart from friends and family, and for me, an aging labrador retriever named Samantha). That’s where I found myself from May to late-June. Here's what that yeilded, in numbers.</p>
<h1 id="the-numbers">The numbers</h1>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Desc</th>
<th>#</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td># of Applications</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of Interviews</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>App/Interview rate</td>
<td>6.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td># of Skype/Video Interviews</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average salary</td>
<td>61,000 CAD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Most common career level</td>
<td>Junior</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Of these, # of university posts</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Of these, # in digital scholarship</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Liaison</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ScholCom</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>College posts</strong></td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Government</strong></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Non-profit</strong></td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Private</strong></td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h1 id="geography">Geography</h1>
<p><img src="https://github.com/cmurgu/cmurgu.github.io/blob/master/images/mapjob.png?raw=true" alt="map of applications"></p>
<p>We speak so seldomly as a community of professionals about this kind of stuff that it makes it difficult to get a general idea of what is considered an average experience. Maybe the notion of &lsquo;average&rsquo; doesn't apply to this. All I can say is that <!-- raw HTML omitted -->I<!-- raw HTML omitted --> struggled. As I got more and more frustrated I had to broaden what I considered &lsquo;the ideal job&rsquo; and compromise with myself — that's ultimately what led to the position that I recently accepted.</p>
<p>And finally, I hope that if I'm ever in position to hire someone — as part of a hiring committee, maybe — I think back to these experiences and affect some sort of change to the hiring process. For example, emailing candidates with intermittent updates, or informing candidates that the position has been filled. It might seem like a small thing, but these gestures free up some much needed mental load for jobseekers.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On Conflating Values</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/07/on-conflating-values/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/07/on-conflating-values/</guid>
            <description>And so, given their pervasive nature and ability “to foster broad changes, both intended and unintended, in the activities that they monitor, social measures deserve closer scholarly attention.” It seems that we have embraced, albeit to different degrees, the practice of ranking institutional repositories. I find this development problematic because it extends the language and logic of markets to an initiative that has heretofore been fueled by magnanimity, author rights, and social justice, first, and capital, second.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And so, given their pervasive nature and ability “to foster broad changes, both intended and unintended, in the activities that they monitor, social measures deserve closer scholarly attention.” It seems that we have embraced, albeit to different degrees, the practice of ranking institutional repositories. I find this development problematic because it extends the language and logic of markets to an initiative that has heretofore been fueled by magnanimity, author rights, and social justice, first, and capital, second.</p>
<p>The <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Ranking Web of Institutional Repositories<!-- raw HTML omitted --> (RWIR), an initiative out of the Cybermetrics Lab at the Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cientificas (Madrid), seeks to <!-- raw HTML omitted -->“to support Open Access initiatives and therefore the free access to scientific publications in an electronic form and to other academic material. The web indicators are used here to measure the global visibility and impact of the scientific repositories.”<!-- raw HTML omitted --> A standard opening. Subsequently, the RWIR’s mission statement devolves into a discourse embedded in market logic: <!-- raw HTML omitted -->“If the web performance of an institution is below the expected position according to their academic excellence, institution authorities should reconsider their web policy, promoting substantial increases of the volume and quality of their electronic publications.”<!-- raw HTML omitted --> The logic here is that once we have established benchmarks with which to judge whether an institution is “picking up the OA slack” via their institutional repositories, we can effectively guilt them into action. In contrast, the institutions that are knocking it out of the park can display another shiny accolade on the proverbial mantle. For those lagging behind, RWIR provides a “Decalogue of good practices” to boost the “position” of the institutional repository, which is ostensibly nothing more than a SEO brochure.</p>
<p>Rankings only work in a state of competition where decisions are predicated on quality indicators (for students, research funding, scholars, and accolades). After all, university administrators anticipate the yearly QS and THE results with baited breath not because of general interest, but because these social statistic mean something to consumers. One must only look at the reactions of high-ranking administrators in the wake of a new set of rankings – in the press and elsewhere – to get a sense of their value. If we focus on publishing, slightly more complicated market forces are at work. The relationship between “top ranked journals” and tenure and promotion committees has engendered a system where authors are competing for coveted real-estate in particular journals. Journal impact factors act as the quality indicator in some fields, whilst in others, formal or informal acknowledgements between peers denote which journals are worth pursuing; in both cases, some form of ranking dictates behaviour.</p>
<p>All of this is moot in the context of institutional repositories. Institutional repositories do not compete against one another for pre- and post-prints, and authors do not deliberate between different institutional repositories for two reasons. First, there’s no incentive to archive one’s work in one institutional repository over another; the oft publicized benefits of making one’s work available in an institutional repository (for instance, citation benefits) is cemented in the act of uploading, not the venue where it makes an appearance. Second, even if research that suggests some institutional repositories are indexed more regularly than others exists, institutional repositories, by their very nature, only support the work of scholars affiliated to that institution. The question, then, is not, “should I archive my research in X or Y repository?”, but simply, “<em>should</em> I make my research available?”.</p>
<p>On one hand I’m delighted to see that Western University’s <em><!-- raw HTML omitted -->Scholarship@Western<!-- raw HTML omitted --></em> and the University of Waterloo’s <!-- raw HTML omitted --><em>UWSpace</em><!-- raw HTML omitted --> – I am currently enrolled and working as a repository manager at Western, and working in the HSS library at Waterloo – are ranked 124th and 134th in the world, and 51st and 57th in North America, respectively. Setting aside the opaque nature of RWIR indicators, these rankings suggest that these institutions are committed to open scholarship. That's great. I’m also not surprised that the University of Toronto’s <!-- raw HTML omitted --><em>TSpace</em> <!-- raw HTML omitted -->and the University of British Columbia’s (beautiful) <!-- raw HTML omitted --><!-- raw HTML omitted -->Open Collections<!-- raw HTML omitted --><!-- raw HTML omitted --> are the top ranked Canadian institutions.</p>
<p>On the other hand, I can imagine a world where institutional repository rankings are used by institutional strategists to market a university’s level of “openness.” National funding bodies, like the RCUK, the Tri-Agencies, and the NSF are already trying to measure the incalculable, like impact, innovation, engagement, and reach: why not add another to the list? The byproduct of this tack would be a renewed sense of urgency in populating respective institutional repositories. To maximize rankings universities will subscribe to three well-known strategies: reallocate funds and resources, develop new policies that mandate certain outcomes, and identify ways of “gaming” the numbers. This would likely result in an increase in the absolute volume of scholarship available in institutional repositories; yet, the end-goal will not be informed by the moral values that we currently purport to uphold, but by a brazen profit motive.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On Metrics and Acknowledgement Texts</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/06/on-metrics-and-acknowledgement-texts/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/06/on-metrics-and-acknowledgement-texts/</guid>
            <description>===
At first glance, these metrics are innocuous. In an increasingly austere environment, measurement and quantitative evaluation have become part and parcel of the machinery of academia at all levels, normalized for provosts, students, and everyone in between. However, having given this a little more thought, I think that the most sinister thing about these metrics is that they&#39;re increasingly being self-imposed; that is, governments, in an act of &amp;lsquo;magnanimity&amp;rsquo;, are encouraging institutions to identify which measures they&#39;d like to be held to account on.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>===</p>
<p>At first glance, these metrics are innocuous. In an increasingly austere environment, measurement and quantitative evaluation have become part and parcel of the machinery of academia at all levels, normalized for provosts, students, and everyone in between. However, having given this a little more thought, I think that the most sinister thing about these metrics is that they're increasingly being self-imposed; that is, governments, in an act of &lsquo;magnanimity&rsquo;, are encouraging institutions to identify which measures they'd like to be held to account on. Having received the proverbial carrot, we seem to have shifted the conversation away from &lsquo;why must we measure?&rsquo; to &lsquo;fine, which measures shall we highlight?&rsquo; I’d like to concentrate on the third aforementioned metric (“Average number of research-funded collaborations/partnerships with industry, government, and NGOs”) for the remainder of this post, and approach it from a perspective informed by my experience in History and my current job as a librarian working in bibliometrics and research impact.</p>
<p>We all want to present the best version of ourselves<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->especially when funding is on the line; institutions of higher learning are no exception. As a result, when the onus of choosing which metrics should be highlighted falls on institutional shoulders, the natural inclination is to choose the ones that are most flattering. My institution is a world-class institution in STEM research and education (I throw around words like &lsquo;Quantum&rsquo; and &lsquo;Nano&rsquo; a few dozen times a day). The publishing culture in STEM fields embraced co-authorship and multi-author publications as the <!-- raw HTML omitted -->modus operandi<!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted -->decades ago. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->In most cases, the very nature of the research requires teams consisting of dozens of researchers, from across the world, doing a variety of tasks that I can't begin to explain. In other cases, individuals are included as authors as a token of gratitude for reading early manuscripts or as a showing of respect. It, therefore, makes sense that they'd highlight international collaboration as a worthwhile measure. The problem is that at some point, co-authorship alone became the standard way of measuring collaborative scholarship, international or otherwise (for studies on co-authorship in STEM see <!-- raw HTML omitted -->this <!-- raw HTML omitted --> and <!-- raw HTML omitted -->this<!-- raw HTML omitted -->).</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>A quick look at <em>Web of Science</em> data (I know this is an imperfect source, but just bear with me) illustrates how standardized measures of collaboration explicitly underprivileged those working in the Arts and Humanities, specifically History.</p>
<p><img src="%7B%7Bbase%7D%7D/images/physics.jpg" alt="Nuclear Physics international collab"></p>
<p><img src="%7B%7Bbase%7D%7D/images/engineering.jpg" alt="Engineering international collab"></p>
<p><img src="%7B%7Bbase%7D%7D/images/history.jpg" alt="History international collab"></p>
<p>These numbers should not be surprising. They represent two different cultures of publishing that I need not describe here. The problem is that, if we begin to subscribe to self-imposed institutional metrics that <!-- raw HTML omitted -->overwhelmingly<!-- raw HTML omitted --> privilege one publishing culture over another, what's to say that those metrics won't facilitate disproportionate or inequitable incentive structures at the faculty level? Again, the most sinister part of this scenario is that we'd be doing it to ourselves. I'm not blind to the realities of academia; measuring research impact and productivity are not capricious trends. We have two options, as I see it: we could dig our feet in the ground and rage against the dying of the light, choosing instead to not engage with metrics in any fashion; or, we could start to think of ways to express to administrators, librarians*, analysts and governments that the work we do is profoundly collaborative.</p>
<p>So, are historians collaborative? I turned to &ldquo;Acknowledgements&rdquo; in research articles published in <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Gender &amp; History <!-- raw HTML omitted -->and the <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Journal of Modern History <!-- raw HTML omitted -->to find out. I've always been interested in acknowledgement texts. Whether in books or research articles, I find that I learn a lot about the person whose work I'm about to engage with from the way that they express gratitude to young graduate students and colleagues (international or otherwise), show humility (or not), and communicate their love to their children and partners. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->This article<!-- raw HTML omitted --> in <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Applied Linguistics <!-- raw HTML omitted -->by Davide Simone Giannoni breaks apart &ldquo;acknowledgement texts&rdquo; into constitutive parts. As Giannoni writes, &ldquo;acknowledgements are staged texts with a coherent rationale governing their rhetorical construction.&rdquo; In general, through a &ldquo;socially-accepted communicative framework,&rdquo; authors articulate their debts &ldquo;with enough ambiguity to reconcile the public and private realms of discourse.&rdquo; Ultimately, &ldquo;if acknowledgements have been discounted as an exercise in flattery, this is largely due to their misuse and exclusion from the peer review process.&rdquo; This is a shame, given that &ldquo;the genre's formulaic, inventory-like appearance conceals a carefully worded rhetoric emphasizing academia's most prized values: cumulative knowledge and intellectual integrity&rdquo; [pg. 23-4]. Can you have these two things without collaboration?</p>
<p>My rushed analysis of an (admittedly anemic) sample of 33 articles published in the last year or so reveals that historians publishing in those journals are surprisingly collaborative, despite publishing as single authors. In <!-- raw HTML omitted -->G&amp;H, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->61% of authors acknowledged that their article would not have been possible were it not for significant edits, comments, and criticisms from <!-- raw HTML omitted -->at least one <!-- raw HTML omitted -->colleague at an institution <!-- raw HTML omitted -->in a country different from their own<!-- raw HTML omitted --> (in some cases the author referenced three or more international collaborators).† In <!-- raw HTML omitted -->JMH, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->a similar result: 64% expressed that they were extremely grateful for suggestions, comments, and edits on early drafts of their articles from colleagues abroad. Here's what these acknowledgements, illustrated as lines or edges, look like on a map:</p>
<p><img src="%7B%7Bbase%7D%7D/images/map.jpg" alt="Map of relationships"></p>
<p>Obviously, I can't confirm just how extensive these collaborations ran, or if they are just &ldquo;exercises in flattery&rdquo;; nonetheless, I would ask the authors the following question: if the publishing culture in the humanities mirrored that of STEM fields, would you feel comfortable listing the colleague to which you expressed your gratitude as a secondary author?‡</p>
<p>I'm not suggesting that we crowd our acknowledgement texts with collaborators (though, I wonder if we should begin a process of reconceptualizing &lsquo;authorship&rsquo; in the humanities, to something like Blaise Cronin and others&rsquo; idea of associated &lsquo;contributorship&rsquo;). Not only are acknowledgements <!-- raw HTML omitted -->not <!-- raw HTML omitted -->a metadata field in most commercial databases, but it would lead to the very same problem that we're seeing in STEM author fields. All of this is to say that we should not clock out at the very mention of measurement: we should pay close attention to the metrics that are chosen <!-- raw HTML omitted -->for <!-- raw HTML omitted -->us, and be present when given the chance to choose <!-- raw HTML omitted -->for ourselves. <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<h1 id="notes">Notes</h1>
<p>* Librarians working in bibliometrics are generally sympathetic and well-informed on the issue.</p>
<p>† It might not surprise you to know that Antoinette Burton came up again and again in the sample.</p>
<h2 id="postscript">PostScript</h2>
<p>‡ Since writing this post I stumbled across Nadine Desrochers, Adele Paul-Hus, and Vincent Lariviere's chapter, &ldquo;The Angle Sum Theory: Exploring the Literature on Acknowledgements in Scholarly Communication,&rdquo; (<!-- raw HTML omitted --><a href="http://crctcs.openum.ca/files/sites/60/2016/05/Desrochers_Paul-Hus_Lariviere_2016.pdf">http://crctcs.openum.ca/files/sites/60/2016/05/Desrochers_Paul-Hus_Lariviere_2016.pdf</a><!-- raw HTML omitted -->) in Cassidy Sugimoto's (ed)<!-- raw HTML omitted -->Theories of Informetrics and Scholarly Communications <!-- raw HTML omitted -->(2016). They do a <!-- raw HTML omitted -->much <!-- raw HTML omitted -->better job explaining acknowledgement texts than I.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Mother tongues</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/05/mother-tongues/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/05/mother-tongues/</guid>
            <description>When I was about 8 or 9 I renounced Romanian and began to think and dream exclusively in English. To renounce my mother tongue was an active decision. I remember the day that I said to myself, &amp;ldquo;English is my language now and I must learn it and embrace it.&amp;rdquo; I said this immediately following a spelling test in which I misspelled &amp;ldquo;Dad&amp;rdquo;; I wrote down &amp;ldquo;Dod.&amp;rdquo; I had just started school.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I was about 8 or 9 I renounced Romanian and began to think and dream exclusively in English. To renounce my mother tongue was an active decision. I remember the day that I said to myself, &ldquo;English is my language now and I must learn it and embrace it.&rdquo; I said this immediately following a spelling test in which I misspelled &ldquo;Dad&rdquo;; I wrote down &ldquo;Dod.&rdquo; I had just started school. What was I thinking? I was <!-- raw HTML omitted -->over<!-- raw HTML omitted -->thinking, in the wrong language. For me North America was a new world—and in this new world English was the key: the key to community, the key to networks, the key to sociality, the key to friendship, the key to culture, the key to citizenship, the key to <!-- raw HTML omitted -->everything<!-- raw HTML omitted -->.</p>
<p>And besides, I could not write well in Romanian; I struggled with grammar and felt as though I was always behind. I was only 7. People would tell me that Romanian &ldquo;is an easy language because it's phonetic and it has very strict rules. You just need to memorize the rules.&rdquo; I could not memorize the rules. Nevertheless, I could speak it fairly well and it was the language I used to think and articulate my thoughts. I recall taking private English lessons with a pleasant man sporting a Tom Selleck moustache. He would have me watch cartoons and we would translate words together and my parents would pay him and I gather they thought I was well on my way to mastering the language; they did not know at the time that I would go on to misspell &ldquo;Dad.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I embraced English as the language of my thoughts and dreams, but there are times when English continues to be a foreign language to me. Sometimes, when I sit down to write, I feel as though we are completely estranged. It is often a bitter struggle and it's why this blog exist (but if my publishing rate is any indication&hellip;) Why is every paragraph a fight, every essay an internal scrap? Would I have a mastery of the metaphor had English been my mother tongue? Would I still need thesaurus.com and Google tabs at the ready to help me find the correct word to articulate a thought? Would I still consider my prose prosaic and flat, neither elegant nor sophisticated?</p>
<p>There is another consequence to abandoning a mother tongue. Yiyun Li recently wrote a moving personal history for the New Yorker titled <!-- raw HTML omitted -->&quot;To Speak is to Blunder.&ldquo;<!-- raw HTML omitted --> It's beautiful and delicate, and you should read it. In it she describes what it was like to abandon Chinese and embrace English as  her &ldquo;public and private language.&rdquo; The following excerpt struck me: &ldquo;Over the years, my brain has banished Chinese. I dream in English. I talk to myself in English. And memories—not only those about America but also those about China—are sorted in English.&rdquo; Renouncing a language affects the way that you recall memories. What does that mean? When I recall a memory I build the scene in English. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->There was a chair and a table and he was there and she was sitting and they were talking and music was playing. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Romanian memories should be remembered in Romanian but I build them in English, too. &ldquo;When one remembers in an adopted language,&rdquo; writes Li, &ldquo;there is a dividing line in the remembrance. What came before could be someone else's life; it might as well be fiction.&rdquo; What happened before, then, is mediated by this other language that is <!-- raw HTML omitted -->at once<!-- raw HTML omitted --> mine and not mine. I'll let Li have the last words because they are perfect, and I wish I had written them: &ldquo;One's relationship with the native language is similar to that with the past. Rarely does a story start where we wish it had, or end where we wish it would.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On DH and Digital Archives</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/04/on-dh-and-digital-archives/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/04/on-dh-and-digital-archives/</guid>
            <description>This post was originally published as a MediaCommons Field Guide. You can read the original, along with other responses on the question of the future of the archive, here. I’ll start off by disclosing that I am notan archivist; my perspective is informed by the time I’ve spent in archives as a researcher, and the work that I’ve been doing recently on digital historiography. In a way, I’m an outsider looking in.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post was originally published as a MediaCommons Field Guide. You can read the original, along with other responses on the question of the future of the archive, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->here. <!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
<p>I’ll start off by disclosing that I am <!-- raw HTML omitted -->not<!-- raw HTML omitted --> an archivist; my perspective is informed by the time I’ve spent in archives as a researcher, and the work that I’ve been doing recently on digital historiography. In a way, I’m an outsider looking in. That being said, historians are introduced to and respect deeply the elements of archival theory that make their work possible, including provenance, authority, and context. I’m also aware that digital technologies have profoundly impacted the way that historians search for, perform, and disseminate research. In particular, historians are increasingly expecting, on one hand, to find primary sources on the web, and on the other, are encouraged, by funding bodies and institutions, to make material available online. This, in turn, has placed added pressure on archivists to allocate increased resources to improving catalogues and item descriptions, and provide full-text documents or high-resolution images whenever possible. The relationship is reciprocal. Practicing digital humanists have taken it upon themselves to develop curated online repositories using a variety of platforms to meet this demand and to support open access initiatives. While this practice is generally positive, I believe that considering an online repository as tantamount to an archive — gestured by our use of the “digital” qualifier — requires some critical attention.</p>
<p>In the most recent edition of the <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Debates in the Digital Humanities<!-- raw HTML omitted --> (available online), Jentery Sayers published a thought provoking piece titled <!-- raw HTML omitted -->“Dropping the Digital.” <!-- raw HTML omitted --> In short, Sayers “ruins” the digital humanities through <!-- raw HTML omitted -->ruination<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, a technique whereby a text is manipulated and subsequently compared to the original text to identify differences and confirm or refute previous assumptions. Sayers “drops the digital” from a corpus, and combs through the product in order “to examine how its absence shapes meaning and interpretation.” Ultimately, Sayers’ essay encourages us to be reflexive about how and why we append “digital” in qualifying research. The way I see it, a comparable act of uncritical qualification is occurring on the web with the recent explosion of so-called “digital archives.”</p>
<p>The proliferation of low-barrier of entry and low cost digital repository and content management systems, like Omeka and DSpace, has led to the creation of hundreds (if not thousands) of online repositories housing digital artifacts. Artifacts are digital copies of analog materials, or repositories of borne digital documents, or both. Importantly, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->non-archivists<!-- raw HTML omitted --> often create these repositories<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->they are open access, and are sometimes referred to as “digital archives.” The final point requires attention. How does “dropping the digital” from “digital archives” inform our understanding of these online repositories? How are they different from the “physical” archive that we are so familiar with?</p>
<p>Perhaps this is all just a natural shift in what the word &ldquo;archive&rdquo; means to people, prompted by digital methodologies and tools. However, I’m in agreement with Kate Theimer as she <!-- raw HTML omitted -->argues<!-- raw HTML omitted --> 
that the colloquial use of the term “archive” to denote simply “a purposeful collection of surrogates” is problematic due to “the potential for a loss of understanding and appreciation of the historical context that archives preserve in their collections, and the unique role that archives play as custodians of materials in this context.” Indeed, the act of archiving is not simply an arrangement of curated artifacts; materials undergo a strict process of appraisal according to principles of provenance, among others. And while archival institutions are not without criticism*, I think it’s important that we remind ourselves of what we’re overlooking when we co-opt the term “archive”, a term laden with symbolic meaning, for our digital repositories. Without a doubt, the digitization work that we undertake in cooperation with institutional libraries and community organizations is significant and worthwhile; however, the very act of attempting to create a “digital archive” is deeply informed by a value system embedded in Western ways of knowing. Ultimately, the creation of digital collections will continue, as it is a trend fueled mainly by principles of accessibility and is therefore commendable and much needed. However, humanities scholars that are turning to and creating these digital resources must think critically about why and how they are created, and how they might affect new scholarship and knowledge.</p>
<h1 id="notes">Notes</h1>
<p>See, for example, Wood, Stacy, et al. &ldquo;Mobilizing records: Re-framing archival description to support human rights.&rdquo; <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Archival Science<!-- raw HTML omitted --> 14 (2014): 397-419.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The new Trump Library</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/11/the-new-trump-library/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/11/the-new-trump-library/</guid>
            <description>About three weeks ago, back when the world made sense and talk of Donald Trump in the Oval Office was almost exclusively preceded by a “wouldn’t it be hilarious if,” Robert Darnton, Carl H. Pforzheimer University Professor and University Librarian Emeritus at Harvard, mused about the future of the Library of Congress in a Clinton administration. “When the new president, if she is Hillary Clinton, moves into the White House,” asks Darnton, “will she unpack her library in the spirit of Walter Benjamin—releasing memories of adventures attached to books?</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About three weeks ago, back when the world made sense and talk of Donald Trump in the Oval Office was almost exclusively preceded by a “wouldn’t it be hilarious if,” Robert Darnton, Carl H. Pforzheimer University Professor and  University Librarian Emeritus at Harvard, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->mused about the future of the Library of Congress in a Clinton administration<!-- raw HTML omitted -->. “When the new president, if she is Hillary Clinton, moves into the White House,” asks Darnton, “will she unpack her library in the spirit of Walter Benjamin—releasing memories of adventures attached to books? Not likely.” A sensible conclusion. Darnton continues, undeterred: “the arrival of a new president at this moment, not long after the dawn of the digital age, could open an opportunity to reorient literature and learning in a way that was envisioned by the Founders of our country, one that would bring books within the reach of the entire citizenry.” This in the wake of President Obama’s precedent-setting appointment of an African-American <!-- raw HTML omitted -->woman, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Dr. Carla Hayden, as the Librarian of Congress. (Hayden’s defence of patron privacy in the wake of the Patriot Act is the stuff of legend in library circles). Darnton must have thought the time ripe: “Two powerful women located at opposite ends of the axis between Capitol Hill and the White House could revive cultural institutions, restore the public domain, and repair the fault lines that run through our information system. More power to them.”</p>
<p>Having reread Darnton’s hopeful article I cannot help but feel a sense of dread. In the piece, Darnton outlines three specific points where Hayden should make ground: support open-access publishing and challenge publisher oligopolies; team up with Google, the Internet Archive, and HathiTrust to kick digitization initiatives into overdrive and broaden access; and, undermine lobbying efforts to extend copyright while bolstering the Fair Access to Science and Technology Research Act (<!-- raw HTML omitted -->FASTR<!-- raw HTML omitted -->). For after-all, “Her library is like no other in the country,” writes Darnton, “It is a national institution, the main repository of our country’s culture.” A tall order, no doubt, but it is likely that Clinton would have supported Hayden in these endeavours — not out of pure altruism, but out of her proven commitment to public goods, like education and <!-- raw HTML omitted -->health<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, and her stance on <!-- raw HTML omitted -->copyright restructuring<!-- raw HTML omitted -->.</p>
<p>What will the Trump library look like as of January? Impossible to tell at the moment, mainly because he hasn’t been forthright about any of these issues. Nevertheless we can tease bits out of his demagoguery.  His market-driven approach to public goods makes everyone that works or thinks about public institutions, like universities and public libraries, quiver; one thing is for certain, Trump will not be the second Carnegie. His open critique of the TPP puts him, strangely enough, on the side of copyright reform; but this is a red-herring. He doesn’t so much care about the absurd copyright agreements proposed by the TPP but the jobs of American workers that would be jeopardized. While he hasn’t gestured to FASRT directly, Trump’s general stance on broadening information access is disquieting. First, it’s clear that Trump has no idea how the internet functions. “We have to go see Bill Gates and a lot of different people that really understand what’s happening,” he shouted. “We have to talk to them maybe in certain areas closing that internet up in some way.” Second, Trump’s disdain of journalism is well-documented, time and time suggesting that he’d like to see libel laws extended to curtail free-speech. And finally, given his criticism of bloated government, it’s possible that Trump will support having the Copyright Office become an independent organization outside the purview of the Library of Congress, opening it up to concentrated lobbying.</p>
<p>Carla Hayden is the most influential information professional in America, but the Librarian of Congress’ voice could not be heard amidst the cacophony following Tuesday’s election. This is telling, I think. I only hope that in the months to come she restates her commitment to fulfilling the mission of the Library of Congress—that is, to broaden access to information for all citizens. Yes, Hayden’s appointment is barrier-breaking. But going forward she has an opportunity to set a precedent for the entire profession. Now is not the time for stereotypical meekness and neutrality: she must be loud, boisterous, and political.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Long distance grieving</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/07/long-distance-grieving/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/07/long-distance-grieving/</guid>
            <description>After the body of his three-year old son was discovered on a Turkish beach (what is now an iconic image), Abdullah Kurdi’s fears were realized; his entire family, including his two sons and wife had drowned after their boat had capsized whilst on the Aegean. Abdullah then had to make an unimaginably difficult telephone call to the relatives that he was ultimately trying to reach in Vancouver, Canada. Abdullah’s sister, Teema, had tried desperately to sponsor the Kurdi family, but her efforts could not sway Chris Alexander’s Ministry of Immigration.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the body of his three-year old son was discovered on a Turkish beach (what is now an iconic image), Abdullah Kurdi’s fears were realized; his entire family, including his two sons and wife had drowned after their boat had capsized whilst on the Aegean. Abdullah then had to make an unimaginably difficult telephone call to the relatives that he was ultimately trying to reach in Vancouver, Canada. Abdullah’s sister, Teema, had tried desperately to sponsor the Kurdi family, but her efforts could not sway Chris Alexander’s Ministry of Immigration. Following these events, sources described Teema as “completely upset and heartbroken.” At once an understatement and curiously accurate; yes, perhaps imagining a heart literally tearing in half — one made of fibrous tissue, not of paper, and gushing blood — is the only way to go about imagining what Teema must have felt. 9,993 kilometers of land and sea separated her from her family — the moon seems closer at night.</p>
<p>Regardless of their country of origin (im)migrants face an array of challenges. Complex bureaucratic measures impede their movement across borders while precarious travel arrangements across seas and war-zones put their lives in serious danger. Other elements, like language and ethnicity, erect barriers that require time and patience to hurdle. Despite these challenges (im)migrants continue to <!-- raw HTML omitted -->leave<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, hopeful to find greener pastures. I’d like to suggest by way of vignette that we consider <!-- raw HTML omitted -->long distance grieving<!-- raw HTML omitted --> as another one of these challenges.</p>
<p>More common: I found out that my grandmother passed away through a <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Facebook<!-- raw HTML omitted --> <!-- raw HTML omitted -->message<!-- raw HTML omitted --> on 12 February 2014, an hour before an exam. “My condolences. I feel awful, and I’m beside you.” I answered with, “What? What happened?” A lull, but I knew. By then <!-- raw HTML omitted -->bunica, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->the woman that raised me until the age of 8, had been battling with pancreatic cancer for almost a decade. I could not make the funeral, but these things happen. What I didn’t think about then, and am most certainly thinking about now, is how difficult it must have been for my mother to deal with it all from a distance of 7,840 kilometers, rooted in place. Her support network made up of only a son and husband. How can we possibly apply theories of bereavement to these scenarios, where traditional family structures and support networks are anemic at best or non-existent, and immense distances deny the immediate closure that we so desperately seek? How do we mitigate the guilt that one might feel for missing births, baptisms, weddings, and funerals, or the beautiful minutia of everyday life?</p>
<p>I’ve framed this in the context of (im)migration, but ex-pats, and those otherwise estranged from their family deal with this form of grief, too. This post was inspired by a colleague’s telling of her father’s experience with long distance grieving, as well as my recent return ‘home.’ It was not until I walked into my late grandmother’s bedroom that I began to feel comfortable without her. A two year delay engendered by circumstances and decisions, largely out of my control, that will continue to ripple, always.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On leaving Montreal</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/07/on-leaving-montreal/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/07/on-leaving-montreal/</guid>
            <description>Yesterday morning I woke up in my bed for the first time in almost a week. Upon waking to the sound of The National’s Apartment Story, I needed a moment to reorient. By the time I recognized the hushed gurgling of boiling radiator water spurting out of ancient pipe-seams and the cushioned prance of the terrier living in the apartment above me the malaise had already set in. “Why does time pass so quickly in Montreal,” I asked myself.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday morning I woke up in my bed for the first time in almost a week. Upon waking to the sound of The National’s <!-- raw HTML omitted --><!-- raw HTML omitted -->Apartment Story<!-- raw HTML omitted --><!-- raw HTML omitted -->, I needed a moment to reorient. By the time I recognized the hushed gurgling of boiling radiator water spurting out of ancient pipe-seams and the cushioned prance of the terrier living in the apartment above me the malaise had already set in. “Why does time pass so quickly in Montreal,” I asked myself.</p>
<p>My story is a conventional one. I lived in Montreal for a year while completing my Master’s degree. With my studies complete, and with funding run-out, I had to depart. Financial pressures and language barriers more-or-less forced me to retreat back to the bridges I had built back in Southern Ontario. I think that I am happy here, with this slower pace of life, most of the time.</p>
<p>Montreal is a transitory place, and many experience it during a liminal period where transition is the only certainty. Despite being fully cognizant of the impermanence of it all, and even cursing its unforgiving winters and (sometimes) unfriendly citizens, I still developed feelings for Montreal. And when I allow myself to reminisce I feel as though I’ve been replaced. I think that another person is reading History at McGill, sitting in the same classrooms and having similar conversations in that room that overlooks Mont Royal. Another person is in my 300sq.ft. apartment, rearranging the the few pieces of furniture I sold to her for pennies on the dollar. Someone else is eating the Mustard Pork Chops at Le Grand Comptoir, drinking what would have been my house wine. Someone else is making plans with my friends, maybe to see the new collection at the Musee de Beaux Arts, or to hammer back a few subsidized pitchers at Thomson House (knowing my friends, probably the latter).</p>
<p>I took it for granted, naturally. There were days, maybe weeks, when I would question why people even settled in Montreal in the first place (did not engage with historical reasons). But over time, as autumn became a frozen hell and that hell became summer, that cold, cultural capital grew on me. I recall navigating the subway and bus network with a tap of the STM card and a mumbled “Ca va bien?”; my dwindling level of patience as I lagged behind groups of confused tourists; mastering the penguin walk across thousands of meters of icy sidewalks; falling on those icy sidewalks; the drinking, and the thinking.</p>
<p>Last week I spent five consecutive days in Montreal and I am grateful. Amid hanging out with dear friends—old and new—and participating in <!-- raw HTML omitted -->an inspiring conference<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, I found time to walk the icy streets of downtown and the Plateau. Much has not changed. I did not emerge from the McGill-College station at the exit that I had intended; and, as if preordained, I slipped and fell on the corner of Mont Royal and l’Esplanade, just like before. I suspect the soreness in my thigh will fade well before my longing for Montreal will. Onwards.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On returning &#39;home&#39;</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/06/on-returning-home/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/06/on-returning-home/</guid>
            <description>In a few days, on 13 June 2016, I’ll be traveling back to Romania for a three week stint. But one cannot return if one has not first lefta place.
Here’s what I can recall:
The soundtrack to the memories of when my family and I emigrated from Romania is overpowered by four repeating bars of weeping. A nondescript white sprinter van, already filled to capacity with other destined emigres, pulled up to the apartment building where my family and I were waiting.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a few days, on 13 June 2016, I’ll be traveling back to Romania for a three week stint. But one cannot <!-- raw HTML omitted -->return <!-- raw HTML omitted -->if one has not first <!-- raw HTML omitted -->left<!-- raw HTML omitted --> a place.</p>
<p>Here’s what I can recall:</p>
<p>The soundtrack to the memories of when my family and I emigrated from Romania is overpowered by four repeating bars of weeping. A nondescript white sprinter van, already filled to capacity with other destined emigres, pulled up to the apartment building where my family and I were waiting. We were overwhelmed by bittersweet nervousness. <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Two honks.<!-- raw HTML omitted --> I was weeping in the lap of my weeping mother. My grandmothers weeped as they embraced their children and their grandchild; my grandfathers shook my father’s hand and wished him “noroc.” They did not know if they’d ever get to see us again. They never would see us again; not those versions of us.</p>
<p>Those versions, when asked “what is your citizenship?” would only have answered with, “Romanian.” Those versions, when asked “where do you live?” would only have answered with, “Suceava.” Those versions of us said goodbye to their families and travelled eight taxing hours  to Bucharest— one final tour of Romanian infrastructure — only to die in an Henri Coandā International Airport terminal.</p>
<p>Is it coincidental (or serendipitous? What say you, John Cusack?) that in the summer that I decide to return to Romania the Romanian national football team decides to get it’s act together and qualify for Euro 2016? You see, for as long as I can remember the Romanians have not been able to qualify for any serious international competition. As a result, I’ve rooted for the English, and the Dutch, and then the English again, before giving up all hope; at every pub I went to I was an imposter, and everyone could tell. What is the point of nationalism if you can’t <!-- raw HTML omitted -->perform it<!-- raw HTML omitted --> every once in a little while?  I will perform this coming summer.<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
We jettison versions of ourselves. Some experiences, like emigration, trigger the process and force a refashioning of the self. But I expect that when I land at Henri Coandā on June 14, I will be greeted by a version of myself and I will welcome his warm embrace. I will ask him if he’d like to join me on my vacation, and if he’d like to root for the <!-- raw HTML omitted -->tricolorii <!-- raw HTML omitted -->together.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On trying to get it right</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/01/on-trying-to-get-it-right/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2016/01/on-trying-to-get-it-right/</guid>
            <description>Edward Samuel Wesley De Cobain entered the Antrim Court dock in March 1893 believing, at least outwardly, that he was innocent.
He was, right up until he was expelled in 1892, a well-liked representative for East Belfast in the House of Commons. His ardent defense of Protestantism, Unionism, organized labour, and Belfast’s working-classes was hardly spotless during his tenure (1886-1892), but it set him aside from the rest and it nevertheless earned him respect from his constituents and fellow Unionists.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Edward Samuel Wesley De Cobain entered the Antrim Court dock in March 1893 believing, at least outwardly, that he was innocent.</p>
<p>He was, right up until he was expelled in 1892, a well-liked representative for East Belfast in the House of Commons. His ardent defense of Protestantism, Unionism, organized labour, and Belfast’s working-classes was hardly spotless during his tenure (1886-1892), but it set him aside from the rest and it nevertheless earned him respect from his constituents and fellow Unionists. He must have thought that his marital status would work against him, but he would have put his own mind at ease, for after all, he was a member of multiple all-male clubs, the Orange-Order and Parliament being among the most worthy of note. Not least, he was a zealous Methodist evangelical; his character witnesses made sure to stress this last bit. So as De Cobain made his way to the dock, shackled, he must have surely thought that if anyone could parry a buggery charge, it would be him. He could not will the jury into agreement.</p>
<p>Over the last year or so I’ve focused on articulating De Cobain’s story, and that process finally culminated with the submission of a manuscript a few weeks back. Before I stumbled over these skeletons, I was considering writing a publishing history of two Victorian working-class periodicals, The British Workman and Workwoman. I was dejected when I found out that someone else had written a lengthy thesis on the very same topic sometime in the late 2000s (kuddos). It’s difficult to put that moment into words. That moment when you realize that an idea that you had been shaping and refining in your mind, convinced by (relying on?) its originality, had already been put into words is trying. If nothing else, I learned an important lesson about thorough preliminary research.</p>
<p>So I went back to what I knew best: the Victorian periodical press. By then I had developed an interest in the history of Victorian sexuality, and the popular homosexual scandals of the late 19th century (Dublin Castle, Cleveland Street, and Wilde) were fresh in my mind. When I first read of De Cobain’s trial in The Times, I thought nothing of it, not because it wasn’t interesting, but because I assumed that other historians had already told (and re-told) his story. I was right, but mostly wrong. Indeed, historians have spilled ink on De Cobain, but all together their efforts total to about five pages of printed text. How many pages have been dedicated to Lord Somerset or Wilde, I wonder?</p>
<p>As I continued to explore De Cobain’s antics I began to periodize the scandal differently. How did him absconding from England in 1891 affect the trial? How did Westminster react? How did the press paint De Cobain? What was he up to whilst in Spain, France, Belgium, and in the United States? What did his family think? Why did he return to face his accusers? Not least, what if the actual trial in March 1893 wasn’t the most important part of this whole thing? I learned very quickly that I was telling a more complete story about De Cobain. But more importantly, I learned that I was using De Cobain’s experiences to tell a story about reactions and tolerances. This was to be a story about voices in the press and otherwise that frothed with self-righteous male indignation against an alleged sexual deviant. This was to be a story about timid voices calling for candor and judicial integrity. This was to be a story about a troubled man searching for answers, both from his brother and from God. This was to be my historiographical contribution.</p>
<p>I write all this because today I received in the mail a number of documents that, I hope, will allow me to write a definitive account of what happened in that courtroom. As fate would have it (or my own incompetence, the jury is out), I discovered these documents after finishing and submitting the final manuscript, so I’m not entirely sure if I’ll have to revise or add to the story that I was trying to tell there. But even if these documents turn out to be a waste of cash, they’ve already reminded me of something that I’d forgotten after I pressed “send” weeks ago: definitive accounts of anything are impossible to craft, but we can try.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The humanities aren&#39;t booming. That&#39;s okay.</title>
            <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2015/12/the-humanities-arent-booming.-thats-okay./</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2015/12/the-humanities-arent-booming.-thats-okay./</guid>
            <description>Peter Mandler, professor of British cultural history at the University of Cambridge, recently published an essayin Aeon (at the risk of sounding like an insufferable dolt, I was readingAeon before it was cool). In what is a well written piece, Mandler establishes something that we already knew very well but needed reminding: humanities enrolment has been more or less static since the 1960s. Moreover, relying on some pretty convincing statistics, Mandler argues that whilerelativenumbers in the humanities have declined, absolute numbers in England, Australia, and the United States have actually increased (mainly due to the increased number of women studying the humanities).</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><!-- raw HTML omitted -->Peter Mandler<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, professor of British cultural history at the University of Cambridge, recently published an <!-- raw HTML omitted -->essay<!-- raw HTML omitted --> in <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Aeon <!-- raw HTML omitted -->(at the risk of sounding like an insufferable dolt, I was reading<!-- raw HTML omitted --> Aeon <!-- raw HTML omitted -->before it was cool). In what is a well written piece, Mandler establishes something that we already knew very well but needed reminding: humanities enrolment has been more or less static since the 1960s. Moreover, relying on some pretty convincing statistics, Mandler argues that while<!-- raw HTML omitted --> relative<!-- raw HTML omitted --> numbers in the humanities have declined, <!-- raw HTML omitted -->absolute <!-- raw HTML omitted -->numbers in England, Australia, and the United States have actually increased (mainly due to the increased number of women studying the humanities). He also establishes historical precedent for the current utilitarian push <!-- raw HTML omitted -->away <!-- raw HTML omitted -->from the humanities, as he contends that “The swing away from the humanities and the sciences [in the 1970s] demonstrated some old lessons. Policymakers had had a very simpleminded understanding of the relationship between education, human capital and economic growth. Their efforts to steer students into the sciences were really a return to earlier, socialist ‘manpower planning’ in favour of certain industrial sectors. In both cases, students had their own ideas of what to study. In both cases, they didn’t respond to government incentives. They were following different signals.” This sounds very familiar.</p>
<p>Indeed, but what of these signals? What of the cultural forces at play that convince young students to spend their years studying Plato, or reading Chaucer? Mandler returns to these enigmatic forces towards the end of his piece. Here I would have liked to see Mandler apply his skills as a cultural historian; instead, he relies on the work of economist Ross Finnie. Mandler writes: “As the Canadian economist Ross Finnie has <!-- raw HTML omitted -->suggested<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, subject choice derives from ‘a complex set of influences, experiences, relationships and developments that are rooted in the family and probably start quite early in an individual’s life – rather than related to a simple well-informed calculation of the future (monetary) costs and benefits made near or at the end of high school’.” Having read the article, Finnie was actually referring to “decisions regarding access to post-secondary education,” and not “subject choice,” but we’ll let Mandler’s misquote slide because Finnie’s comment is totally vague and can still apply. I found it curious that a cultural historian would rely so heavily on statistics and ignore an opportunity to <!-- raw HTML omitted -->do <!-- raw HTML omitted -->history. At the same time, I shouldn’t be surprised: quantitative evidence has always carried more weight. Nevertheless, his essay seems to have been well received by professional historians and graduate students, while general audiences keep on in ignorance.</p>
<p>Mandler’s positive take on the current landscape of the humanities is a welcomed breath of fresh air. It certainly challenges the “crisis” narrative, and for those initiated enough to care, it should provide for brief moment of respite. With all that being said, I found it interesting that Mandler ignored (side-stepped?) Canadian statistics in his work. Here are my conclusions on recent enrolment statistics.</p>
<p>This is not the first time that the skies have seemed so dark. According to <!-- raw HTML omitted --> StatsCan post-secondary 1st cycle students data<!-- raw HTML omitted -->, enrolment in the humanities dropped by 18.8% from 1992-93 (125,319) to 1999-2000 (101,736), only to rebound dramatically within the decade with humanities enrolment (from History and English Literature, to Maritime Studies and French Language and Literature) across the country increasing by 16.8% from 2004-05 (122,712) to 2009-10 (143,331). These favourable increases were prompted by increased enrolment in Manitoba, British Columbia, and Ontario. However, since 2009-10, humanities enrolment has seen a dramatic decrease to the tune of 12% (now hovering around 126,000 students). And what of humanities enrolment relative to <!-- raw HTML omitted -->all<!-- raw HTML omitted --> 1st Cycle enrolment? Whereas in 1992-93 humanities enrolment constituted 22.5% of all post-secondary 1st Cycle students (601,764 total students), that proportion is closer to 13.7% today (921,600 total students).</p>
<p>So what does this all mean? Yes, the number of students studying the humanities has not changed very much over the last 20+ years in Canada. But according to StatsCan 1st Cycle enrollment data, the number of students enrolling in humanities programs relative to the number of students enrolling in all other post-secondary programs has gone down by ~10%, and I’m doubtful that the trend will discontinue. While it is true that the number of students studying the humanities has remained steady, that won’t be of much consolation to program heads and deans. A recent <!-- raw HTML omitted -->Quarterly Update<!-- raw HTML omitted --> from the President of my institution (a small to medium sized comprehensive research university) placed this into perspective. According to Alan Wildeman, “Most noticeably, enrolment in FAHSS has dropped from 44% to 34% of total student enrolments, while Engineering has risen from 9% to 15%.” These numbers have far reaching consequences on program funding, faculty appointments, and capital expenditure priorities; perhaps it’s not enough to look at absolute numbers.</p>
<p>This all suggests to me that policymakers and university administrators have been quite successful in presenting certain “signals,” effectively selling students (literally, with beautiful physical space, or theoretically, with promises of increased return on investment) the idea of post-secondary education in non-humanities programs. And yes, I think humanities departments at Canadian universities need to rethink the way they brand themselves to prospective students. But I also think that the virtues of an education in the humanities are largely engendered by its scale; it’s not commercial or towering, but substantial, intimate, and effective.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
