<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cal Murgu</title>
    <link>https://calmurgu.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Cal Murgu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://calmurgu.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Confessions of a reformed Omeka acolyte. Minimalist options for digital exhibitions</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/11/confessions-of-a-reformed-omeka-acolyte.-minimalist-options-for-digital-exhibitions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/11/confessions-of-a-reformed-omeka-acolyte.-minimalist-options-for-digital-exhibitions/</guid>
      <description>While a Digital Projects Coordinator at the University of Windsor in 2015-16, I remember thinking that Omeka would revolutionize the way we create and teach about digital exhibits, metadata, and the subtle acts involved in digital collecting. Here was a relatively lightweight CMS that enabled us to spin up new instances almost immediately. With set-up a breeze, we could focus our attention on the intellectual work of arrangement, description, and narrative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/cv/</guid>
      <description>Last updated: 12/15/2019
For PDF click here: PDF
Education  MLIS, Western University (2018)
 Awarded Beckman Gold Medal in LIS  MA, History, McGill University (2015)
 MRP: “Innocence is as Innocence Does!”: Edward S.W. De Cobain, Hegemonic Masculinity, and the Politics of Scandal in Victorian Britain, 1884-1893 (N.B: Later published as article in Gender &amp;amp; History.)  BA, Honours History, Literature Minor, University of Windsor (2014)
Library Experience  Research, Instruction, and Digital Humanities Librarian, New College of Florida (2018)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Librarian/Faculty Interaction Data with R</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/07/visualizing-librarian/faculty-interaction-data-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/07/visualizing-librarian/faculty-interaction-data-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to Jesse Sadler and their blog for this information. It was very, very helpful for a novice like me. I find that I learn best when I have a specific project to practice with, with tangible goals that I can associate with my work. This is an example of one such project.
This post is an attempt at using R to develop a process for using Librarian/Faculty interaction data in a meaningful way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I grew up in Windsor, Ontario, Canada, a stone&amp;rsquo;s throw from Detroit, Michigan. I studied History at the University of Windsor and McGill University in Montreal. In September 2016, I moved to London, Canada to study Library Science at Western University. From May to December 2017 I worked in Bibliometrics at the University of Waterloo. I am currently a Librarian working in digital scholarship and instruction at the New College of Florida.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/__index/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/__index/</guid>
      <description>Last updated: 07/09/2019
Table of Contents  Education Experience  Library Experience Other Experience   Scholarship  Journals Non-Reviewed Conferences   Continuing Education Awards Professional Membership Media Teaching Service Skills  Education  MLIS, Western University (2018)
 Awarded Beckman Gold Medal in LIS  MA, History, McGill University (2015)
 MRP: “Innocence is as Innocence Does!”: Edward S.W. De Cobain, Hegemonic Masculinity, and the Politics of Scandal in Victorian Britain, 1884-1893 N.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s time to go, Jeff</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/02/its-time-to-go-jeff/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2019/02/its-time-to-go-jeff/</guid>
      <description>When Jeffrey Beall retired from the Auroria Library at the University of Colorado at Denver in March 2018, half of the scholarly publishing world applauded him for his efforts against &amp;ldquo;predatory publishers.&amp;rdquo; The other half let out a massive sigh of relief. Beall&amp;rsquo;s retirement succeeded a prolonged period of scandal in some academic circles.
In the years leading up to his retirement, Beall began to receive increasingly negative attention for his now infamous &amp;ldquo;Beall&amp;rsquo;s list,&amp;rdquo; a blacklist of potentially predatory publishers that he himself had curated since 2008 (presumably on his free time, and not while working at the Auroria Library).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On library jobs</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2018/07/on-library-jobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2018/07/on-library-jobs/</guid>
      <description>This post is primarily for graduate students in LIS that are looking for some anecdotal information about what it’s like to look for work in the information field. It&amp;rsquo;s a pretty nasty proposition. In general, this post is like many others in an emerging genre, prompted by Melanie Stefan&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;A CV of Failures&amp;rdquo; and Johanes Haushofer&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;CV of Failures,&amp;quot; which attempt to shine a spotlight on all of the things academics apply for and fail to get, be it a grant, scholarship, publication, or job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Conflating Values</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/07/on-conflating-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/07/on-conflating-values/</guid>
      <description>And so, given their pervasive nature and ability “to foster broad changes, both intended and unintended, in the activities that they monitor, social measures deserve closer scholarly attention.” It seems that we have embraced, albeit to different degrees, the practice of ranking institutional repositories. I find this development problematic because it extends the language and logic of markets to an initiative that has heretofore been fueled by magnanimity, author rights, and social justice, first, and capital, second.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Metrics and Acknowledgement Texts</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/06/on-metrics-and-acknowledgement-texts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/06/on-metrics-and-acknowledgement-texts/</guid>
      <description>===
At first glance, these metrics are innocuous. In an increasingly austere environment, measurement and quantitative evaluation have become part and parcel of the machinery of academia at all levels, normalized for provosts, students, and everyone in between. However, having given this a little more thought, I think that the most sinister thing about these metrics is that they&amp;rsquo;re increasingly being self-imposed; that is, governments, in an act of &amp;lsquo;magnanimity&amp;rsquo;, are encouraging institutions to identify which measures they&amp;rsquo;d like to be held to account on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mother tongues</title>
      <link>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/05/mother-tongues/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://calmurgu.com/posts/2017/05/mother-tongues/</guid>
      <description>When I was about 8 or 9 I renounced Romanian and began to think and dream exclusively in English. To renounce my mother tongue was an active decision. I remember the day that I said to myself, &amp;ldquo;English is my language now and I must learn it and embrace it.&amp;rdquo; I said this immediately following a spelling test in which I misspelled &amp;ldquo;Dad&amp;rdquo;; I wrote down &amp;ldquo;Dod.&amp;rdquo; I had just started school.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>